<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Homepage on Popa Ioan Alexandru</title><link>https://alex11br.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Homepage on Popa Ioan Alexandru</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Feel free to do whatever with my content, unless another stricter license is specified.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 22:11:46 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://alex11br.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Goodbye, Jekyll! Welcome, Hugo!</title><link>https://alex11br.github.io/posts/welcome-to-hugo/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 21:44:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://alex11br.github.io/posts/welcome-to-hugo/</guid><description>If you&amp;rsquo;re seeing this, this site is now running with Hugo.
When I first started using Github Pages, I used Jekyll as a static site generator. It had the advantage of being very easy to get up and running: just create a repo in which you put the markdown files you want to turn into web pages, with other eventual raw HTML you might have, commit, push, and voila, you have a working website.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;re seeing this, this site is now running with Hugo.</p>
<p>When I first started using Github Pages, I used Jekyll as a static site generator. It had the advantage of being very easy to get up and running: just create a repo in which you put the markdown files you want to turn into web pages, with other eventual raw HTML you might have, commit, push, and voila, you have a working website.</p>
<p>That being said, while getting Jekyll to work on the Github Pages remote which publishes the site is super easy, getting it to work on my machines so that I can properly see whatever changes I make to the site isn&rsquo;t that easy. My experience with setting up Ruby on my machines has always been a really painful one, having to fight error after error, and as someone who doesn&rsquo;t use Ruby anywhere else, this is not what I want to go through to see my changes in my blogs. This experience just makes me want to stay away from using Ruby to make apps, I don&rsquo;t like it at all.</p>
<p>Maybe I&rsquo;m just too dumb to use Ruby and its apps, but I just don&rsquo;t like having to set it up. So I tried to look for other static site generators that don&rsquo;t make me install all sorts of <em>dubious runtimes and dependencies</em>, and I found 2 viable alternatives: Zola and Hugo - both written in statically compiled languages (the opposite of <em>dubious runtimes and dependencies</em> - that&rsquo;s pretty cool 😎).</p>
<p>I ended up choosing Hugo, as I found <a href="https://github.com/adityatelange/hugo-PaperMod">this theme</a> that I could get configured just the way I wanted my blog to be - yay! While some people on the internet appreciated Zola&rsquo;s simplicity as opposed to Hugo, I just could not get my way around its simplicity&hellip;</p>
<p>I hope this post will not be the only one I post here, I hope to write more stuff here, but I haven&rsquo;t a good track record on this. Maybe this is an opportunity to start fresh, to have a better plan with this online space&hellip; We&rsquo;ll see.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://alex11br.github.io/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://alex11br.github.io/contact/</guid><description>There are many social platforms or whatever that I use. Here are a select few:
Email: alexioanpopa11@gmail.com Github: ALEX11BR</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are many social platforms or whatever that I use. Here are a select few:</p>
<ul>
<li>Email: <a href="mailto:alexioanpopa11@gmail.com">alexioanpopa11@gmail.com</a></li>
<li>Github: <a href="https://github.com/ALEX11BR">ALEX11BR</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Projects</title><link>https://alex11br.github.io/projects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://alex11br.github.io/projects/</guid><description>I have various projects that I&amp;rsquo;ve made across the years of my existence. As I am a Romanian, some of the projects presented are in Romanian; they will get a Romanian flag(🇷🇴).
Compunere de oscilații paralele (source) 🇷🇴 Proportional election methods simulation (source) AltSFX is an alternative sound effects pack for OpenTTD, and is available through the in-game online content system. ThemeChanger lets you change GUI themes on Linux with ease.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have various projects that I&rsquo;ve made across the years of my existence. As I am a Romanian, some of the projects presented are in Romanian; they will get a Romanian flag(🇷🇴).</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/fizoscomp">Compunere de oscilații paralele</a> (<a href="https://github.com/ALEX11BR/fizoscom">source</a>) 🇷🇴</li>
<li><a href="/proportional-election-simulation">Proportional election methods simulation</a> (<a href="https://github.com/ALEX11BR/proportional-election-simulation">source</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ALEX11BR/AltSFX">AltSFX</a> is an alternative sound effects pack for OpenTTD, and is available through the in-game online content system.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ALEX11BR/ThemeChanger">ThemeChanger</a> lets you change GUI themes on Linux with ease.</li>
<li>As a linux user I have various <a href="https://github.com/ALEX11BR/dotfiles">dotfiles</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I&rsquo;m not only a programmer, but I also have other miscellaneous projects:</p>
<ul>
<li>I (used to) make photos of public transportation vehicles, available <a href="https://alexioanpopa.blogspot.com/p/poze-vehicule-transport-in-comun.html">here</a>. 🇷🇴</li>
<li>I also make some maps, that can be seen <a href="https://alexioanpopa.blogspot.com/search/label/H%C4%83r%C8%9Bi">here</a>. 🇷🇴</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>